<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>J S</title>
    <description></description>
    <link>http://localhost:4000/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Sat, 22 Aug 2020 23:12:10 -0400</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 22 Aug 2020 23:12:10 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.8.7</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>How would an upside-down candle burn?</title>
        <description>&lt;!-- ![grid26] --&gt;
&lt;!--exc--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As every child knows, sometimes it’s fun to do something exactly wrong.  In that spirit, what would happen if you burned a candle upside-down?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To take a guess, we need to understand how candles work.  Their simplicity is deceptive; burning candles are actually complex systems with many interacting parts and processes.  They illustrate a vast array of different chemical and physical processes so elegantly that the great physicist Michael Faraday gave a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=RrHnLXMTOWM&quot;&gt;series of lectures&lt;/a&gt; on candles, not only explaining the mechanisms by which candles work but using them to demonstrate effects from from turbulence to buoyancy to blackbody radiation and explain the chemistry of flame.  Candle flames are such common sights that we often overlook their complicated anatomy; look at one closely and you’re likely to see a number of features, from the blue glow at the bottom to the tapering of the tip, that everybody recognizes but few people could actually explain if asked.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Explaining all of candle physics would take a textbook, but for this question, we only need to think about things that change when the candle is turned upside down, which simplifies the problem a lot.  The most obvious is that the heat of the flame, normally drawn up and away because hot air’s less dense than cold air, will flow directly into the tip of the candle.  Under normal operation, the tip of the candle wax is just hot enough to melt a small pool of wax but not hot enough to boil it, putting it at between 50 °C and 370 °C.  By contrast, the spot one wick-length above the tip of the wick is in the core of the flame, with a temperature in the vicinity of 1000 °C.  If you somehow just flipped the flame upside down, the flame would melt the wax a lot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Candles are systems with a lot of feedback, however; the flame melts the wax which feeds the flame and so on.  We’ve decided how changing the flame would affect the wax, but how would the change in the wax then feed back and affect the flame?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The flame’s shape would obviously change, deflected by the block of wax in its way.  How would the burning itself change, though?  An important fact is that in candles, the wax only combusts as a vapor.  It starts as a solid, is melted and drawn up into the wick and into the heart of the flame by capillary action, and is vaporized by the high heat.  It’s only then that combusion happens - the hot, vaporized wax molecules react with oxygen and give off heat, perpetuating the process.  In the upside-down candle, more wax would be in the region of high heat, so there would be more hot surface area for vapor to escape from.  This means that wax would vaporize and burn at a higher rate, which, all else being equal, should give a bigger flame.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, there’s a problem with this situation.  This augmented flame would melt a lot of wax; what if it melts wax faster than it can vaporize it?  All the excess wax might run and fall off the candle unburnt, so the candle would both run out faster and drip a lot.  There’s a stranger possibility, though.  What if the flame melts wax that floods down over the wick too thickly for the flame to vaporize it in time and snuffs it out?  Like Icarus, it’d die from melting wax and its own zeal.  This was my guess for what would happen to the upside-down candle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also asked friends to guess how an upside-down candle would burn and got around 10 responses.  Most people either gave the self-snuffing scenario - let’s call it scenario (1) - or the second, self-sustaining scenario - say, (2).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
   &lt;img src=&quot;https://james-simon.github.io/img/candle_scenarios.png&quot; width=&quot;30%&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To answer this question, I dangled a candle, set up another for comparison, and lit them.  &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=tJv4IOTvCWY&quot;&gt;A video of the result is here.&lt;/a&gt;  Forgive the subpar quality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This matched scenario (1) - the candle initially burns, but once it starts to melt wax it’s quickly put out.  Out of curiosity, though, I ran another trial with the same candle.  The result was wholly different, matching scenario (2).  It turns out that the same candle can follow either path, probably depending on the initial shape of the tip and wick.  The phase-space of this upside-down candle has two basins of attraction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=XKAtwxw7SWk&quot;&gt;Here’s a video of the second trial.&lt;/a&gt;  Most people were right at least once.  Nobody, however, predicted the stalactite.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 20 Aug 2020 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/physics/2020/08/20/upside-down-candle.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/physics/2020/08/20/upside-down-candle.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>physics</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Messing with the postal service</title>
        <description>&lt;!-- ![grid26] --&gt;
&lt;!--exc--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The United States’ postal system is an institution of renown, a conduit for objects and information older than the Constitution.  Even now, amid financial difficulties and numerous competing ways to send things, it’s still remarkably effective - neither snow nor hail nor remote destinations nor heavy loads fazes the US’ army of postal workers.  This raises a natural question: can we find something that does?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Out of related curiosity, over years I’ve mailed a slew of things I’d guess were new to postmen.  These included a letter with a hole in the middle (arrived), a pentagonal letter (arrived), an origami crane (arrived), a pack of sticky notes with an instruction on the back for any postal worker reading it to take one note (arrived missing many), a dollar bill addressed like a postcard (returned, in an envelope, due to not having an envelope), a note in an envelope made of dollar bills (arrived), and a literal stick with an address written on it (arrived in a bag with an apology for any damages).  A piece of crumbling bark, two letters tied together, and a spherical rock the size of a golf ball weren’t successfully delivered.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why’d some of these objects arrive while others didn’t?  The USPS’ regulations and pricing seem to assume that anything sent is either a letter or in a large envelope or box, but I haven’t found anything explicitly forbidding sending things without boxes.  The lack of explicit rules probably means postal workers have a lot of leeway in deciding what to do with weird items, which makes sense and fits the data - I don’t see a sharp line that separates the successes from the failures above, but the failed items do seem a little more obnoxious.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are an infinite number of ways to mess with the postal service, though, and alone I’ve tried only a handful.  The theme’s worth some more variations.  I once led a group of children at a summer camp in mailing random objects, but only so much is accessible in the middle of the woods.  At the end of the spring 2020 semester, I and 11 other members of my physics cohort formed a group to mail each other weird things in the style of a secret Santa.  The group, dubbed the University Society of Postal Shenanigans (USPS), finished its first round in June.  Here are our results, ordered subjectively by the mailed object’s ridiculousness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;halloween-decoration&quot;&gt;Halloween decoration&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Delivered after several weeks&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
   &lt;img src=&quot;https://james-simon.github.io/img/usps/ween.jpg&quot; width=&quot;300px&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;mint-box&quot;&gt;Mint box&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not accepted via mailbox delivery and rejected at a post office by a persnickety employee&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
   &lt;img src=&quot;https://james-simon.github.io/img/usps/mints.jpg&quot; width=&quot;300px&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;hand-sanitizer&quot;&gt;Hand sanitizer&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Delivered&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
   &lt;img src=&quot;https://james-simon.github.io/img/usps/sanitizer.jpg&quot; width=&quot;300px&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;bonne-maman-jam-lid&quot;&gt;Bonne Maman jam lid&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not delivered&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;anticannibalism-bracelet&quot;&gt;Anticannibalism bracelet&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Delivered&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
   &lt;img src=&quot;https://james-simon.github.io/img/usps/strap.jpg&quot; width=&quot;300px&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;glove&quot;&gt;Glove&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not delivered&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
   &lt;img src=&quot;https://james-simon.github.io/img/usps/glove.jpg&quot; width=&quot;300px&quot; /&gt;
   &lt;img src=&quot;https://james-simon.github.io/img/usps/gloveback.jpg&quot; width=&quot;300px&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;lemon-from-my-backyard-with-address-and-urgent-written-on-it-in-sharpie-mailed-within-berkeley&quot;&gt;Lemon from my backyard with address and URGENT written on it in Sharpie mailed within Berkeley&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Delivered in a few days&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
   &lt;img src=&quot;https://james-simon.github.io/img/usps/lemon.jpg&quot; width=&quot;300px&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;lemon-coincidentally-picked-from-another-bay-area-backyard-and-mailed-to-berkeley&quot;&gt;Lemon coincidentally picked from another Bay area backyard and mailed to Berkeley&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Delivered&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
   &lt;img src=&quot;https://james-simon.github.io/img/usps/lemon2.jpg&quot; width=&quot;300px&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;origami-box-containing-three-origami-cranes&quot;&gt;Origami box containing three origami cranes&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Delivered&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
   &lt;img src=&quot;https://james-simon.github.io/img/usps/origami_box.jpg&quot; width=&quot;300px&quot; /&gt;
   &lt;img src=&quot;https://james-simon.github.io/img/usps/origami_crane.jpg&quot; width=&quot;300px&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;lone-stamp-with-address-and-odd-message-on-back&quot;&gt;Lone stamp with address and odd message on back&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not delivered&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
   &lt;img src=&quot;https://james-simon.github.io/img/usps/stamp_front.jpg&quot; height=&quot;350px&quot; /&gt;
   &lt;img src=&quot;https://james-simon.github.io/img/usps/stamp_back.jpg&quot; height=&quot;350px&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;chicago-flag-socks-with-an-address-and-stamps-sewn-into-one&quot;&gt;Chicago flag socks with an address and stamps sewn into one&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Delivered (credit to Madeline Bernstein for the quality item)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
   &lt;img src=&quot;https://james-simon.github.io/img/usps/sock.png&quot; width=&quot;300px&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;3d-ball-maze&quot;&gt;3D ball maze&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Delivered despite having too little postage.  As the postman collected perhaps the best $2.55 I’ve ever spent, he made it clear with his manner that he’d never seen something like this and wasn’t going to miss the chance to make fun of it&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
   &lt;img src=&quot;https://james-simon.github.io/img/usps/maze.png&quot; width=&quot;300px&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;dehydrated-celery-stalk-partially-wrapped-in-duct-tape&quot;&gt;Dehydrated celery stalk partially wrapped in duct tape&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not Delivered&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are a few clear conclusions we can draw from these experiments.  First, the sheer probability of the postal service delivering something weird is shockingly high.  Second, they’re more likely to deliver something when there’s no way to give it back to the sender - the mint box was refusable, and my single dollar had a return address, and both failed, while almost nothing else risky had a return address.  Third, though object ridiculousness wasn’t very correlated with success, the apparent value of objects was - the ball maze, socks, and hand sanitizer all have some obvious use, while the celery, jam lid, and single glove don’t.  A natural combination of these conclusions is that the postal service will probably deliver anything weird they can’t return as long as it seems important enough.  I’d bet you could mail basically anything - a seat cushion, a balloon, a small speaker constantly emitting obscenities - if you permanently attached it to something that looks like a bill with no return address.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The USPS’ experiments will continue, but I’d love to hear from anyone else who’s tried pushing the envelope of the postal system.  Please tell me of your experiments by writing a message on the exterior of a full-size replica of a blue public mailbox and mailing it to the Berkeley physics department.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 12 Jul 2020 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/mail/2020/07/12/mail-shenanigans.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/mail/2020/07/12/mail-shenanigans.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>mail</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Common ground</title>
        <description>&lt;!-- ![grid26] --&gt;
&lt;!--exc--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;America’s polarization is increasingly dire, and with national focus perpetually on divisive issues, both liberals and conservatives often see the other as genuine enemies with whom cooperation’s impossible. There’s a severe lack of sincere dialogue between the left and the right, but that fact makes honest, humanizing conversations with the opposition more precious now than ever. To that end, and to prove that common ground could be found, I, quite liberal, messaged a friend who’s quite conservative for a discussion. Though we began firing off opposing views on divisive topics, with a little thought we found much unexpected agreement and eventually reached a reasonably shared view of pressing problems. Here’s an outline of everything we agreed on, a map of some oft-undiscussed common ground most arguing liberals and conservatives might not realize they both stand on. My hope’s that it might serve as a blueprint for others’ conversations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Police brutality is wrong and should be punished&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Racism exists in 2020 and is a problem&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;From Hollywood to academia to boardrooms, there are many sectors of society in which whiteness is implicitly the default, and even in 2020 this often leads to minorities feeling like outsiders due to their race&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;There are many policies from redlining to the War on Drugs to school funding mechanisms that disproportionately hurt poor communities, which are often largely black or hispanic&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Peaceful protesting is commendable and should never be met with violence&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The word ‘racist’ has extreme connotations, and it’s usually more productive to call someone’s implicit racism ‘ignorance’ or ‘insensitivity’&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Police obviously do some good, and we shouldn’t rush to abolish all police&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The slogan ‘fuck the police’ is unproductive&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Issues often get politicized when they don’t need to be&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Be careful not to share fake news&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Donating to groups like Equal Opportunity Schools, Children of Promise, and Wings for Kids is a clear, apolitical way to make a difference&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Police brutality isn’t the doing of a small fraction of ‘bad cops’ among the ‘good cops’; what’re the odds four for four of George Floyd’s attackers happened to be ‘bad’? They’re questions of group psychology and police culture. Real solutions should involve changing training, increasing police accountability and oversight, reversing unnecessary police militarization, and resolving the noted problem of using police to address too wide a variety of needs. The four-for-four probability argument is one I feel liberals could make more clearly against the ‘few bad cops’ statement.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Media severely biases people’s perceptions of police and protester violence. I’d seen a headline about a pregnant woman hit in the stomach by a rubber bullet, while she’d seen a story about protesters who’d refused to let a car with a sick child through. Given that there were protests in every major city in the US, it’s no shock things like these happened, but because they’re emotionally potent, it’s easy to get riled up when a news outlet or FB algorithm shows you one. It’s more important to focus on broad trends and statistics when possible.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Much of racial inequality is due to racist history and cycles of poverty as opposed to current racism. She thought the national focus should be on investing in poor black communities to fix problems at their roots instead of pinning guilt on police and current racism. While plenty of studies have shown proof of current racism and that fact should be broadly understood, and police abuse of power is prevalent and merits reform, I basically agree; police reform alone won’t fix racial inequality. The question of police blame has become divisive, with conservatives largely defending the police; how’d that happen when there are clearly problems with law enforcement? Maybe it’s because police brutality is more glaring and simpler to address than broad socioeconomic issues, so it’s an easy target for both reform efforts and anger, making it look like the dominant liberal view is that police are the main problem.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Rioting and looting shouldn’t be excused. Our society considers crimes less severe if they’re done in the heat of passion, but they’re still crimes, and though the recent riots are perhaps more understandable because of their motivation and the emotion they’ve brought to the nation’s attention, they’re still highly damaging and often selfish. Excusing these completely is a minority view among liberals but still seems to cause a lot of understandable frustration among conservatives who see it as a mainstream view, which detracts from discussion of more important issues.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Liberals can be very intolerant of conservatives. I’d noticed this but was shocked at the extent my friend described; in her words, “if I shared a [BLM] post but shared the portions I disagree with I’d be called out for not agreeing wholeheartedly, but if I’m silent I’m called out for being silent.” “I fear that putting a conservative sticker will almost definitely lead to vandalism on my car in Richmond.” “I know conservatives who have to put up with liberal rants all day at work and can’t say a thing or else they’ll lose their work relationships and promotion opportunities or even their job.” That sort of thing’s much less obvious from a liberal perspective, so I, for one, believe her. There’s definitely a perception among some liberals that some ideas are so clearly right that anyone with an objection or caveat is automatically morally inferior, with no need for further investigation, and though I agree with most of said ideas, that attitude’s a problem and being aware of it might help give liberals some understanding of conservatives’ perspectives.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When a prominent leader makes a comment that’s widely interpreted as racist, if it wasn’t meant that way, that leader should be clear in explaining the intended meaning and disavowing the racist interpretation.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It’s worth listening to each other.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When factions face off, spears bristling, perhaps the boldest, most important place to stand is in the middle with hands extended to either side. Polarization in the US is as real a crisis as the coronavirus, but unlike the virus, you have significant power to fight it directly.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 04 Jul 2020 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/society/2020/07/04/common-ground.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/society/2020/07/04/common-ground.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>society</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>What would happen if you made a planet out of fish?</title>
        <description>&lt;!-- ![grid26] --&gt;
&lt;!--exc--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the fall of 2019, Ryan Roberts and I gave a talk to high schoolers at Berkeley Splash on analyzing absurd scenarios with real physics.  His talk elucidated what would happen if you put an egg inside the beampipe of the Large Hadron Collider, but I wanted to answer a deep question even a small child could ask.  My talk was on that age-old conundrum: what would happen if you made a planet entirely out of fish?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Part of the beauty of physics is that, if you have the right rules, you can consider absurd scenarios far beyond the realm of possibility and figure out &lt;em&gt;what would actually happen&lt;/em&gt;. In the history of physics, this has led to major breakthroughs; Einstein was famous for using imagined scenarios to derive new physics. Our goal here is less lofty: we want to know what would happen if you put enough fish together in space to make a planet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, let’s imagine how this will happen. Our fish of choice will be the haddock (&lt;em&gt;Melanogrammus aeglefinus&lt;/em&gt;), a 10-kg-max fish well-adapted to the waters of the North Atlantic and poorly adapted to the vacuum of space. Real solar systems start as rotating disks of gas, with a star forming in the center and planets gradually condensing out of the matter in the disk. Let’s just remove a young star’s accretion disk and replace it with an equal mass of live haddock.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
   &lt;img src=&quot;https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/UPX6xTzmv-5uKYMGUgktYwdS36AJWZoLeQOoIOvbsAPPW-5sFaCBgU6af30GjaXDuwUqFh5Z5u5PI09i_J-giIqtAqIljJRZ3BYexq41VyC0iYYWrSaSNLcmNpYiZE_RMzNfn03M&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first thing that’ll happen is that the fish will get much bigger. In a vacuum there’s no air to push against the internal pressure of the fish, so they’ll expand, as happened to dogs in &lt;a href=&quot;https://ntrs.nasa.gov/archive/nasa/casi.ntrs.nasa.gov/19660005052.pdf&quot;&gt;disturbing experiments in the 60s&lt;/a&gt;. The water in parts of the fish would also boil, not because it’s hot, but because it’s at a very low pressure. To understand why that happens, you can imagine that even with atmospheric-pressure water, occasionally little bubbles of vapor form inside it, but the pressure of the water compresses them back into nothing, the vapor’s reabsorbed, and the bubbles go away. If that water is in a zero-pressure environment, however, that opposing force is gone, and nothing prevents bubbles from forming, so it boils. The escaping vapor might then condense into tiny ice crystals depending on how far from the star this is happening.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We now have a proto-solar-system of dead haddock orbiting a star, bathed in water vapor and ice crystals. Wonderful! Now what happens? As the cloud of fish orbits the star, fish will occasionally hit each other. Usually they’ll bounce off, but with each collision a small bit of kinetic energy will be lost, and the fish will have more similar velocities after the collision than before it. Eventually, fish will collide so gently that they’ll stick together due to their tiny gravitational attraction. Small blobs of fish will collide to form bigger blobs, while the biggest blobs pick up lots of individual fish and small blobs as they move through the cloud, like a combination of the games Katamari Damacy and Feeding Frenzy. Eventually, most of the fish will be concentrated in big asteroid-like blobs. Since astronomers like to name everything, let’s do the same; let’s focus on one fish-blob and call it &lt;strong&gt;Blobfish&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
   &lt;img src=&quot;https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/H0JSdunlzk8eyowWVPB_N6MJEskml4JKeZ4n7NFR7HH0G9utLHMM4QBYMyJy4e0RRaz51BjvNl3Ts9YaUrncev3xnFCkdXr147JY3fKquHrf0K2E7KEQ_hUzW8NUa6OQLab_khbE&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The size of Blobfish depends on how many fish it contains; more precisely, the radius scales as N1/3, where N is the number of fish in it. If we have, say, a million fish, we’ll get a fish asteroid with a radius of about 10 meters. Depending on its orbit, this fish asteroid might eventually pass near the star it’s orbiting, trailing dust and gas behind it, and it could also be ejected from the star system if it passes too close to a much bigger body, but at that size there isn’t much more it would do that’s interesting. We’ll need to add more fish.
What about a trillion? With &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;10^{12}&lt;/script&gt; haddock, we’d have a radius of a little over 1 km. Though much larger, this is still just a fish asteroid. Let’s jump up a lot. With &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;10^{23}&lt;/script&gt; haddock - around one for every molecule of water in a cubic centimeter - we have a planet that’s a little like Earth. It has a radius of around 6000 km, and enough mass to be comparable to the rocky planets in our solar system. Let’s call it &lt;strong&gt;Rockfish&lt;/strong&gt;. We now have an astronomical body made entirely of fish!
Well, at least they started as fish. The inside of a planet after its formation can be very hot; the main reason is that the kinetic energy that the proto-planets lost in each collision while forming the planet was turned into heat. Because the fish attract each other gravitationally, there’s a lot of gravitational potential energy that’s now present as heat. The energy balance works out the same as if we’d built up this planet entirely by dropping meteors on it, which shows that each bit of mass should have enough thermal energy to move very fast.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
   &lt;img src=&quot;https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/W1s4UmENLaan6tI0RPEHeOWgeGrzlQ_bcyyfZbCTSzaIUczb1Y2YnhaAWdkdzbu60CNv83dWXQu7y6HsnCHAKexGXLVzQSKqD0MtwqqFwPJ_V2SPTEMC6Bzm-Yj3KlIRWAQRW_bb&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How hot is Rockfish? If you form a planet with a mass M and a radius R by bringing together small bits of mass initially spread very far apart, you get a total potential energy loss of &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\frac{3M^2G}{5R}&lt;/script&gt;, which we’ll assume gets turned into heat. For a rough approximation, let’s assume that our fish planet has the density and heat capacity of water. The resulting temperature scales as N2/3, so a 1 km asteroid would have negligible heat of much less than a degree, but Rockfish would have a temperature 1500 K, around the melting point of iron and definitely hot enough to do serious damage to a fish. Now we have enough mass and thermal energy for new things to happen on our planet.
In the intense heat, the fish are quickly reduced to their basic chemical constituents: the elements composing our fish will be mostly free to rearrange themselves to minimize their energy. People haven’t studied the basic chemical constituents of haddock closely, but the chemistry of humans is well-studied and pretty similar, geologically speaking. By mass, the human body is roughly 65% oxygen, 20% carbon, and 10% hydrogen, with at least 0.1% of nitrogen, calcium, phosphorous, potassium, sulfur, sodium, chlorine, and magnesium, with traces of many other elements. Let’s assume the fish are the same - they’ll have higher concentrations of chlorine, magnesium, and sodium from saltwater, but we won’t be precise enough for that to matter. The question of what happens to our planet is now mostly a question of geology and chemistry.
Planets naturally form layers of different densities, with the heaviest elements (iron and nickel in the Earth’s case) sinking to the planet’s core. Let’s give this newborn planet a few million years to separate into layers, then analyze it in layers from the core upwards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
   &lt;img src=&quot;https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/l-5cT5tXLPu5FgHlSymTrj3mNRaWqr9tmtQTvwRbyrR2mNPQpiap7zPYD5_a1kipyH9zIqoAheKPNOiJZb3xjkAqoIKlAwJREh42BvbEomBPXDnad6quTSKStsV7Y52Ddkv1t-Ug&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the center of Rockfish, there would be a small inner core of the dense trace metals, like iron and mercury, found in fish. However, the densest thing likely to form in large quantities is actually pure carbon; graphite has a density roughly 2.3 times that of water, while the densest of the major metallic components is magnesium, which is about 1.5 times as dense as water when liquid. The core of this planet would be mostly carbon, and that carbon’s under very high pressure - the pressure at the core of a planet is proportional to M2/R4, which is again proportional to N2/3, so as we’ve added more fish that pressure has gotten large, reaching 50000 times the pressure of Earth’s atmosphere. Actually, at these temperatures and pressures, carbon is most stable as diamond! It turns out that this planet could easily have a core of solid diamond, which is probably its coolest feature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just outside the carbon core, we’d find a layer containing calcium, potassium, magnesium, and other metals denser than water but less dense than carbon. It might also contain oxygen like the Earth’s mantle. This layer would be much thinner than the Earth’s outer core, but it might be similar in one key way. The Earth’s magnetic field is caused by a complicated, poorly-understood process called the geodynamo, in which a flowing, conducting fluid like Earth’s liquid Fe-Ni outer core generates a magnetic field in a feedback loop. Our molten metal layer could do the same; it’s entirely plausible that this planet would have a magnetic field.
Above that, there would be massive oceans. Water is most of the mass of a fish, so there would be enormous salty oceans with a depth of thousands of kilometers. If this planet ends up with an Earth-like moon, the tides would be massive. There would likely be undersea vents on the ocean floor. Above the ocean there’d be an atmosphere with tons of water and oxygen, possibly also with carbon dioxide and gases like methane that could be released by fish in the original accretion disk. Due to the water content in the atmosphere, there would be dense clouds and a strong greenhouse effect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What about life? Fish are good fertilizer: by definition, this planet contains abundances of all the necessary chemical ingredients for life, and it likely has a magnetic field to shield it from ionizing radiation. If it’s orbiting a star within the right distance range, there’s no reason this mass graveyard of fish couldn’t be a birthplace of life. Actually, it turns out some bacteria can survive in the vacuum of space, so maybe some bacteria would be dormant in frozen fish or form small ecosystems on fish asteroids near the star, and then seed life on Rockfish. That’s total speculation on my part, but there would be a lot of chances for it to happen - there’d be something like &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;10^{40}&lt;/script&gt; live bacteria at the start of the experiment - and the creativity of the evolution of bacteria is surprising.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What if we added more fish?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we keep adding fish to this body, the temperature and pressure at the center will increase. When there are around &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;10^{28}&lt;/script&gt; fish, the body will have roughly 10% the mass of the Sun, and fusion of hydrogen can start in its core. Let’s call the resulting object &lt;strong&gt;Starfish&lt;/strong&gt;. Most of the hydrogen will likely have floated to the surface, however, so fusion would probably be slower than normal. However, if we increase this by a factor of 100, with &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;10^{30}&lt;/script&gt; fish and 10 solar masses, Starfish will have enough heat and pressure to fuse carbon and oxygen, its main constituents. At that size, the star will be a blue giant that might live 30 million years before either dying in a supernova or by releasing its outer layers to form a stellar nebula.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’d be silly to stop now. What if we added more fish?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Einstein’s equations tell us that enough mass-energy within a given radius will collapse into a black hole, so in theory, if we just keep adding fish, that’s what we’ll end up with. We can call it &lt;strong&gt;Blackfish&lt;/strong&gt;. Black holes are also created in supernovae of massive stars, and since we have a star anyways, let’s consider that case. The causes, results, and mechanisms of supernovae vary a lot between stars with different masses and compositions, but as a rough figure, a star with 100 solar masses is likely to form a black hole. This corresponds to &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;2*10^{31}&lt;/script&gt; fish, roughly 1000 for every atom in a human body. This star will have a relatively short lifetime of millions of years, eventually dying in a supernova that leaves behind a black hole. As far as current physics knows, that’s the end; if you add any more fish, you just get a bigger black hole.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 17 Jun 2020 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/physics/2020/06/17/fish-planet.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/physics/2020/06/17/fish-planet.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>physics</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>How hard do you have to hit a chicken to cook it?</title>
        <description>&lt;!-- ![grid26] --&gt;
&lt;!--exc--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some questions are timeless, innocent yet penetrating in their simplicity. Why is the sky blue? Why do things fall? How hard must one hit a chicken to cook it? It is this last mystery of the universe that we discuss today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.boredpanda.com/physics-major-calculates-how-hard-to-slap-chicken-to-cook-it/?utm_source=google&amp;amp;utm_medium=organic&amp;amp;utm_campaign=organic&quot;&gt;classic solution&lt;/a&gt; in which someone calculated that, if you slap a chicken at 3726 mph, it will be cooked. However, this analysis just calculates how hard you’d have to hit a chicken to get it to cooking temperature; you need to keep it at that temperature for it to cook. One slap won’t work unless you get it so hot that it cooks while it’s cooling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A real answer to this vital conundrum needs to consider how fast a chicken cools. A body at a nonzero temperature is constantly radiating energy as blackbody radiation; this is what you see in incandescent lightbulbs or when glass glows during glassblowing. To keep an object at a given temperature, you have to continuously give it the same energy it’s radiating away. A typical-sized chicken at 165 F is radiating away roughly 2000 watts of power, around 300 times the power used in a fluorescent lightbulb. To avoid losing any heat to contact with the air, let’s assume we dangle the chicken from a string in a large vacuum chamber. Let’s also assume you and a few friends are hitting the chicken with baseball bats like a pinata. In order to keep the chicken at 165 F for the minutes needed to cook it, it would be enough to have four people each hitting it once a second with a bat swung at 75 mph, about the speed with which a pro swings. Four major-league baseball players wearing pressure suits in a vacuum chamber each hitting a dangling chicken with a baseball bat once a second could cook it in a few minutes.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 17 Jun 2020 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/physics/2020/06/17/chicken-cooking.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/physics/2020/06/17/chicken-cooking.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>physics</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The expected cost of breaking quarantine</title>
        <description>&lt;!-- ![grid26] --&gt;
&lt;!--exc--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In countries around the world, a common message has issued from government to populace: isolate yourselves, or covid-19 will take more lives.  Most of the US is now under some degree of quarantine.  For the average American, though, the risks of coronavirus are minimal; isolation serves more as a means to shield society at large than as individual protection.  That raises a natural question, though: since quarantine in the US isn’t enforced, how bad would it be to see people anyways?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s a worldwide effort to predict the effects of coronavirus given different courses of societal action, but there’s been less focus on the risks of individual actions.  With the climate crisis, we have both global predictions and ways to gauge individuals’ impacts; a person’s carbon footprint is quantifiable.  With this pandemic, however, we agree that social distancing is crucial, but personal impact isn’t quantified.  As every person strikes a balance between isolation and normalcy - few people simply never go outside - it would help to have some way to gauge just how bad social interaction is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One way to get a rough sense of the effects of different actions is with simple models of disease spread through a population.  As a first stab at a calculation, consider a population of &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;N&lt;/script&gt; people of which &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;c&lt;/script&gt; currently have a disease.  This disease shows no symptoms, so infected people don’t know to isolate, and it never goes away - these &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;c&lt;/script&gt; people are contagious forever.  As a model for spreading, imagine people interact in randomly-drawn pairs, and if one person has the disease and the other doesn’t, the first will give it to the second.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s clear from the start that the whole population’s eventually going to be infected, but one thing we can quantify is &lt;em&gt;how many people get the disease earlier than they would’ve otherwise if one person doesn’t isolate.&lt;/em&gt;  Every infected person’s going to have a number of people downstream from them including people they’ve infected, people those people have infected, and so on.  In this model, people downstream of you would’ve stayed healthy longer if you’d isolated.  Because all the &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;N - c&lt;/script&gt; uninfected people will eventually be downstream from one of the &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;c&lt;/script&gt; infected people, each of the &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;c&lt;/script&gt; infected people expects to have &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\frac{N - c}{c}&lt;/script&gt; people downstream on average.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now imagine person &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;i&lt;/script&gt; and person &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;j&lt;/script&gt; have contact.  If one is infected and the other is uninfected, which happens with new-case probability &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;p_{\text{nc}} = \frac{2c(N - c)}{N^2}&lt;/script&gt;, a new infected person is created; there are now &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;c + 1&lt;/script&gt; sick people, and the extra infected person has on average &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\frac{N - c - 1}{c + 1}&lt;/script&gt; people downstream who will get sick sooner than they would’ve if person &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;i&lt;/script&gt; and person &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;j&lt;/script&gt; hadn’t interacted.  Including the one of those two who got sick, that’s &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;x = \frac{N - c - 1}{c + 1} + 1 = \frac{N}{c + 1}&lt;/script&gt; infections sped up per new case.  Multiplying by the probability and assuming that &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;N, c \gg 1&lt;/script&gt; gives &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;p_{\text{nc}} x = \frac{2c(N - c)}{N^2}\frac{N}{c + 1} \approx \frac{2(N - c)}{N}&lt;/script&gt;.  When &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;c \ll N&lt;/script&gt;, like it is for the coronavirus, this is roughly &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;2&lt;/script&gt;; in this model, interacting with a random person you could’ve avoided leads to two cases of the disease happening earlier than they would’ve otherwise.  This is approximately true whether the current rate is one in fifty or one in a million; if the probability of a stranger having the disease is lower, then the expected number of downstream infections is proportionally higher.  This number of two infections is just an average - it has a high statistical uncertainty - but reasoning based on averages makes sense in this case.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This isn’t really how coronavirus works, though; covid doesn’t last forever, and people with symptoms can isolate.  To make the model more realistic, let’s say there are &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;c&lt;/script&gt; &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;c&lt;/script&gt;urrently &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;c&lt;/script&gt;orona-&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;c&lt;/script&gt;ontagious people who have the disease but either haven’t shown symptoms yet or won’t ever and &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;r&lt;/script&gt; people who are either currently showing symptoms and isolating or have already gotten better, so they can’t infect anyone else and are &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;r&lt;/script&gt;emoved from the calculation.  For now, we’ll still assume every person eventually gets the disease.  The new probability of a new case when two people interact is &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;p'_{\text{nc}} = \frac{2c(N - c - r)}{N^2}&lt;/script&gt;, and the expected number of downstream people from a new infected person (plus that person) is &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;x' = \frac{N - r}{c + 1}&lt;/script&gt;.  The expected number of accelerated infections per interaction is &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;p'_{\text{nc}}x' = \frac{2(N - r)(N - c - r)}{N^2}&lt;/script&gt;.  For the coronavirus, &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;r,c \ll N&lt;/script&gt; - only a small fraction of the population has been infected - so this simplifies to 2 again.  Even allowing for isolation and resistance, interacting with a random person leads to, on average, two cases of coronavirus happening earlier than they would’ve. &lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So far, we’ve assumed that everybody’s going to get the coronavirus.  That’s not likely, though; in a worst-case scenario, once ~70% of the population has been infected, herd immunity should extinguish the virus, and before then either a vaccine or extensive contact tracing could stop the virus’ spread.  If the endgame of the pandemic is herd immunity, individual actions will affect when people get the disease, but the total number of cases will mostly be set by the herd immunity threshold.  However, if a vaccine stops the spread, for example, timing matters more.  Suppose that 1000 people in a large state currently have the virus, and by the time a vaccine stops the pandemic 100000 new people have gotten it.  If the population’s much bigger than 100000, the cases don’t interact, and we can estimate that if there were 1001 contagious people to begin with, there would’ve been 100100 new cases instead; every current case causes 100 future cases.  As before, let’s say &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;N&lt;/script&gt; is the population, &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;r&lt;/script&gt; people are recovered or symptomatic, &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;c&lt;/script&gt; people are contagious and asymptomatic, and &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;s&lt;/script&gt; people are currently uninfected but will eventually get the disease (&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;s&lt;/script&gt;urely &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;s&lt;/script&gt;ometime &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;s&lt;/script&gt;icken).  Assuming &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;s&lt;/script&gt; is small compared to the total number of uninfected people as discussed (&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;s \ll N - r - c&lt;/script&gt;), the average current infection causes &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;y = s/c&lt;/script&gt; preventable cases.  The probability of an interaction generating a new case is still &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;p'_{\text{nc}} = \frac{2c(N - c - r)}{N^2}&lt;/script&gt;, which means that, in this model of a terminating pandemic, each extra interaction between strangers causes &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;p'_{\text{nc}} y = \frac{2s(N - c - r)}{N^2} \approx \frac{2s}{N}&lt;/script&gt; preventable cases.  This means that, optimistically, if ~25% of the population eventually gets coronavirus and a much smaller percentage has it now, every unnecessary interaction with a stranger will cause ~0.5 extra cases of the disease.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This model has a few key shortcomings:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Interactions aren’t all or nothing; most interactions fall between six feet of separation and sharing bodily fluids, so the final numbers should be reduced proportional to how likely the interaction in question is to spread coronavirus.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Actual estimates of the number of people who’ll get coronavirus are often over 50%, in which case cases interfere with each other and the final result will be less than &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\frac{2s}{N}&lt;/script&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Interactions aren’t random, and interacting with someone you’ve interacted with before isn’t as bad as talking to a stranger.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If society works harder to stop the pandemic the worse the pandemic is, then there’s an unconsidered second order effect in which more cases of the coronavirus now can lead to fewer later.  Also, as mentioned, if the endgame of the pandemic is herd immunity, then in terms of total number of cases, it’s almost irrelevant what an individual does.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are all reasons why our calculation of &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\frac{2s}{N}&lt;/script&gt; extra cases per interaction is an overestimate.  A slightly more complicated calculation might be able to account for (2), and we can deal with (3) by saying that this calculation only applies to interactions with people you don’t already see very frequently and counts back-to-back interactions with the same person as one interaction.  (4) deals with different ways the pandemic could play out; nobody can predict that, but for now let’s suppose we’re in a regime where the calculation applies (where more cases now basically lead to more total cases); perhaps there’s only a 50% chance of that, in which case you could reduce the final expected cost by a factor of two.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(1), the most glaring flaw, is one we can account for, though.  This analysis assumed every contaminated interaction had 100% probability of spreading the disease; what is that probability in reality?  It would take an expert and a lot of information on the exact details of the interaction to give a precise answer, but we can make a decent approximation.  Epidemiologists use &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;R_0&lt;/script&gt; to represent the average number of people each person with coronavirus infects.  If &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;R_0 &gt; 1&lt;/script&gt;, the pandemic is getting exponentially worse, and if &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;% &lt;![CDATA[
R_0 &lt; 1 %]]&gt;&lt;/script&gt;, it’s getting better.  &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;R_0&lt;/script&gt; is estimated at 2 to 3 before social distancing, but it now varies greatly; however, since the number of new cases per day in the US &lt;a href=&quot;https://news.google.com/covid19/map?hl=en-US&amp;amp;gl=US&amp;amp;ceid=US%3Aen&amp;amp;mid=%2Fm%2F09c7w0&quot;&gt;has been pretty constant for a few weeks&lt;/a&gt; (though it varies by state), we can estimate &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;R_0 \approx 1&lt;/script&gt;.  If the average US citizen with coronavirus interacts with &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;q&lt;/script&gt; people while infectious, then each interaction has  a &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;1/q&lt;/script&gt; probability of transmission.  Asymptomatic patients are contagious for about two weeks, while symptomatic patients are contagious for a few days before their symptoms start and they hopefully isolate, and with a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.hopkinsguides.com/hopkins/view/Johns_Hopkins_ABX_Guide/540747/all/Coronavirus_COVID_19__SARS_CoV_2_&quot;&gt;25-50% probability of a case being asymptomatic&lt;/a&gt; let’s estimate that the average contagious period is five days.  How many interactions do you think the average American has in five days during this quarantine?  I couldn’t find polling data estimating this, but in Berkeley it seems like most people only get close to a handful of other people without a mask.  Let’s give a highball estimate of 20 relatively close interactions over five days and suppose that only these close interactions will spread the virus.  That puts each close, maskless interaction at a 5% chance of spreading the virus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With this estimate, we can adjust our final number: assuming 25% of the population gets coronavirus before it’s stopped and each contaminated interaction has a 5% chance of spreading the disease, we calculate that each time you have a close interaction with a new person it causes 0.5*0.05 = 0.025 new, preventable cases of coronavirus.  With a death rate of 1%, this gives 0.00025 deaths/interaction.  That’s quite high - odds of 1 in 4000 - and with the assumptions we’ve made, it might even be an underestimate.  If a fraction of a life seems intangible, Prof. Oskar Hallatschek pointed out that governments quantify the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Value_of_life&quot;&gt;value of a human life&lt;/a&gt;; it usually falls around a few million dollars.  If the government fined people for interactions in proportion to their risk to human life, with this estimate the fine would be around $1000.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These calculations are rough; though I think their logic is sound, they are carved with a heavy chisel designed only to give the right basic shape.  That is far better than nothing, though, and the hazy figure of a 0.025% chance of causing the end of a human life when interacting with a stranger is a far more tangible motivation than a government mandate to stay inside for the vague public good.  It gives a tool for reasoning; some things, like doctor’s visits, are clearly worth the risk, while others clearly aren’t, and though in most cases the right thing might’ve been intuitive, in borderline cases it helps to have a risk in mind.  At one step above the individual level, with restaurants and their ilk considering reopening, that risk of 1 in 4000 quickly compounds; if just 10 people all interact, that’s &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;10 + 9 + ... + 1 = 55&lt;/script&gt; interactions, with over a 1% chance of causing a death, and that’s not accounting for the fact that interactions with people who’ve just interacted are riskier than normal.  If 100 people share germs at a concert, that gives 5050 interactions, over one statistical death, but that’s a wild underestimate for the same reason.  At a time when the US population is getting anxious and rash, it helps to have even a rough estimate of the risks involved as an aid to rationality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Someone I talked to after posting this pointed out that the number of downstream people equalling the number of accelerated infections doesn’t make sense.  He’s right - it’s actually possible for the original infection tree to catch up to the new branch.  The simplest case is when the first random contact in the model happens to be between the two people who had the unnecessary contact we’re considering - it doesn’t matter if they interacted because they’re about to interact again, and everybody who’s downstream of the extra patient would’ve gotten sick at the same time anyways.  The numbers of accelerated cases are actually just upper bounds.  I’ve left the analysis there because it explains variables and ideas used in the rest of the post, which this problem doesn’t affect. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 17 May 2020 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/stats/2020/05/17/covid-calculation.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/stats/2020/05/17/covid-calculation.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>stats</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
